even if you sleep great you could still
benefit from taking melatonin and you
want to take as much Melatonin as you
can
tolerate so Dave a melatonin well it
really is a miracle molecule now
everybody knows I take 600 milligrams a
night I'm it
melatonin as Dave has pointed out does
not suppress your own production because
it is not regulated by a negative
feedback loop people only associate
melatonin for sleep and jet lag that's
not my primary motivation behind
melatonin melatonin is a very potent
antioxidant free radical scavenger it's
free radicals that damage DNA and lead
to cancer that's why melatonin can be
used to treat and prevent cancers like
breast prostate and coloral cancer also
protects your mitochondria it does so
many wonderful things that people just
don't know about but like I said if they
did it should be Front Page News every
day so I know you're a big proponent of
melatonin so tell me how you use it in
your population of mday that you're
Consulting with well Bellin is just so
damn good for you that's why it's not
front page news right there's no money
to be made in it that's right so
melatonin is is wonderful as you said
melatonin is the body's Chief
antioxidant and I for the last six
months have been going on a deep dive
down uh is it Dr Russell writer is that
his surname um there's also a guy Dr
John Lawrence Laurence I'm probably
pronouncing it wrong he wrote them
um yeah Miracle yeah yeah um so i' I've
watched all the content I I have gotten
myself recently up to 120 milligrams of
melatonin and I titrated up quite
gradually well I not that gradually I
titrated up very gradually to about 20
and then I moved up in Greater
increments from there and I think there
are a lot of misconceptions around
melatonin particularly the idea that you
only want to take it in minimal amounts
occasionally if you're changing time
zone or whatever that was on this idea
that melatonin has some kind of negative
feedback loop like testosterone does
that was debunked a decade ago
thoroughly it's just that a lot of the
people on the internet who speak very
loudly about things who are often
selling other sleep supplements by the
way are saying you want to avoid
melatonin for all these reasons but you
also want to take a whole bunch of other
antioxidant supplements for to do the
same thing that melatonin does right
it's it's ridiculous so melatonin is
fantastic and I have found it to be
particularly fantastic for people who
have well basically the more stress the
body is under the more you can benefit
from taking melatonin because melatonin
is going to support the body being under
stress the thing that I have
particularly found melatonin to shine
for is intractable um chronic
inflammatory conditions like autoimmune
conditions um particularly uh
endometriosis in women um I don't really
work with women but the other thing that
I found it really useful for is people
with spinal issues or physical pain that
prevents them from getting comfortable
at night and sleeping properly two birds
one stone um so melatonin is a profound
antio oxidant and a lot of the things
that people are looking for antioxidant
benefits for melatonin is wonderful for
we have incredibly higher levels when
we're children and that's why children
tend to be more protected against these
diseases of Aging that we see in in
older populations but the other thing
that we also have to consider is that
when they're looking at studies and
saying to take three to five milligrams
of melatonin because that restores
natural production restores natural
production of older people who were
living in a world that's artificially
lit 247 that's not optimal melatonin
levels so I think that you should take
as much I think every single P person
should take as much Melatonin as they
can tolerate I think a lot of people
there's there's a couple of theories as
to why some people get that groggy
morning after effect one is that they
metabolize it slowly and should take it
before dinner the other is they may be
having a sort of detox reaction I think
both of those are viable but I think the
best way to do it is just titrate up
gradually over time make sure you get
morning sun which you should be doing
anyway and I have only found more
benefits have come from taking more
melatonin do have two spinal injuries
which may be why I get so much benefit
from it but every time I take more
melatonin my wife notices that my skin
looks better my wife notices that I
physically look better um so melatonin
is wonderful I highly recom like when
people say oh I sleep well so I don't
need to take melatonin no go no no no no
no melatonin is an it's we're looking at
it like pregnanolone and DHEA we're
looking at it as a antioxidant
protective Health promoting Health
restoring agents particularly useful if
you're sick and you want to even if you
sleep great you could still benefit from
taking melatonin and you want to take as
much Melatonin as you can tolerate and
you also you want to take a micronized
pharmaceutical grade version of it so
that it gradually gets released in the
gut so you don't get a big spike that's
just going to throw your body's Rhythm
out and yeah as as you know melatonin
wonderful yes you're you're dead on Dave
so people understand that look the
typical dose as daveid pointed out for
sleep is typically a low dose that's
recommended but if you look start
looking at the medical literature look
at some of the meta analysis that have
been done the anti-cancer effects come
in around 20 to 40 milligrams per night
so it's a much higher dose and there's
no harm in taking more than that once
again people will spend an extraordinary
amount of money for antioxidants and all
these foods and drinks and supplements
none of them hold a candle to melatonin
none of them remember hormones are
bullets supplements are BBS it's just
the way that it is so I'm yes as you
know I'm a huge proponent of melatonin I
and now look when you read the book uh
by John look we're not going to take it
rectly okay we're gonna take it orally
like the study do okay you can't vet
every book you know and there's some
good things in there but you know
sometimes you know there's these books
and you have to say no now where did
that really come from so so no let's
don't take melatone erectly people if
you read the miracle molecule by by John
is uh let's let's take it orally like
they do in the studies um that that's
that's an important uh you know fact to
point out all
right